Guide to the G. King Walters academic service papers, 1954-2006 UA 295
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
G. King Walters academic service at Rice University papers
1954-2006
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Walters, G. King
UA 295
1 Linear Feet (1 box)
The G. King Walters academic service papers represent Walters' participation on committees and task forces at Rice University. Walters graduated from Rice Institute in 1953 with a degree in physics. He was hired by Rice as a Physics professor in 1963. Walters remained at Rice through retirement in 1999 and beyond, advancing through the professorial ranks to chairman of the physics department, assistant dean of natural sciences, and dean of natural sciences.
Biographical / Historical
Born in Baton Rouge, Louisiana, in 1931, G. King Walters moved to Houston at the age of 5, attended public schools, graduating from San Jacinto High School in 1949. Matriculating at Rice University in 1949, he majored in physics and was elected to Phi Beta Kappa and Sigma Xi in 1952. After graduating with honors in 1953, he went to Duke University, where he earned his doctorate in physics in 1956. He remained at Duke until 1957 as a National Science Foundation Postdoctoral Fellow. Between 1957 and 1963, when he was hired by Rice, he distinguished himself as a research scientist with Texas Instruments in Dallas. Walters remained at Rice through retirement in 1999 and beyond, advancing through the professorial ranks to chairman of the physics department, assistant dean of natural sciences, and dean of natural sciences.
Walters' areas of specialization were atomic, molecular, and condensed matter physics. In the 70's he conducted pioneering work on excimer lasers that came to be widely used to print semiconductor chips. Experiments he designed and conducted using an atomic accelerator in the now gone Bonner Nuclear Laboratory at Rice formed the basis for very sensitive devices called magnetic anomaly detectors. This technology was used by the U.S. military to detect Soviet nuclear submarines. The devices were also used in space exploration vehicles. In the 80's some of Walters' research, sponsored by the Department of Energy and the Houston-based Robert A. Welch Foundation, included studies of the physics of high-power lasers for possible application in power generation by laser fusion, and investigations of solid surfaces important in industrial catalysis. Subsequent research of his has found practical application as an improved MRI device, which can image the lungs when a patient breathes in polarized helium or xenon gas.
In 1977-78 Walters was awarded a Guggenheim Fellowship, which was followed soon after by his election to Fellowship in the American Association for the Advancement of Science. In addition to authoring a wide range of publications, he has provided editorial leadership for the Journal of Geophysical Research, Case Studies in Atomic Physics, and Reviews of Modern Physics. He served as an elected member of the governing council of the American Physical Society as well as in other positions in national scientific organizations.
In addition to serving as a highly regarded teacher and directing 29 doctoral students, King Walters participated very actively in the structural operations of Rice. His committee work included the Athletic Review Committee and the Faculty Advisory Committee on Retirement. He was a member of three important search committees, for university president in 1984-85, for provost in 1993-94, and for librarian in 1995-96.
A distinctive honor Walters received at the end of his career was the establishment of a one million dollar endowed fund in his name. He directed that awards made from the fund annually are to be used for research innovation in the Rice department of physics.
Scope and Contents
The G. King Walters academic service papers represent Walters' participation on committees and task forces at Rice University. Walters graduated from Rice Institute in 1953 with a degree in physics. He was hired by Rice as a Physics professor in 1963. Walters remained at Rice through retirement in 1999 and beyond, advancing through the professorial ranks to chairman of the physics department, assistant dean of natural sciences, and dean of natural sciences.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is restricted and requires permission of the Head of the Woodson Research Center for access.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred from the office of Walters in 2011.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges
Document Types
reports; minutes (administrative records); letters (correspondence); notes
Places
Rice University
- Presidential Search Committee, 1984-1985; 146356
  - Presidential Search Committee: Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1984-1985; 146357 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Presidential Search Committee: General Information, 1984-1985; 146358 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Presidential Search Committee: Press Release, 1984-1985; 146359 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Award Nominations, 2005-2006; 146360
  - Ronald Sass- Gold Medal Nomination, 2005; 146361 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jim Newman- Distinguished Alumni Nomination, 2005; 146365 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Norman G. Einspruch- Rice University Distinguished Alumni Nomination, 2005; 146366 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Norman G. Einspruch- Highland Park High School Distinguished Alumni, 2005; 146367 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Randall G. Hulet, 2006; 146368 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ad Hoc Faculty Advisory Committee on Retirement, 1998; 146362
  - Report of Ad Hoc Faculty Advisory Committee on Retirement, 1998; 146363 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Retirement Committee, 1998; 146364 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Athletic Review Committee, 1992-1994; 146369
  - Athletic Review Committee, 1992; 146370 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Athletic Admissions Procedure Changes, 1994; 146371 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Athletic Review Committee Minutes and Correspondence, 1992-1994; 146373 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Athletic Review Committee Reports, 1992-1994; 146372 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Harold E. Rorschach Memorial Lecture, 1995-2006; 146374
  - Harold E. Rorschach Memorial Lecture, 1995-2006; 146375 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Nils Muench- Rice University Distinguished Alumni Award Nomination, 1996; 146376 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Inaugural Harold E. Rorschach, Jr. Memorial Lecture, 1995; 146377 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Search Committees, 1993-1996; 146379
  - Provost Search, 1993-1994; 146380 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Librarian Search, 1995-1996; 146381 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Task Force, 1969-1977; 146383
  - 1969 Statement to the Rice Board, 146384 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Task Force on Consolidation and Enhancement, 1976; 146385 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Task Force on Consolidation and Enhancement, 1977; 146386 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- General Correspondence, 146391
  - The Cornerstone Article on Professor Harold A. Wilson, 2002; 146392 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Physics Equipment by Arthur D. Little, Inc., 1954; 146393 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Natural Science Minor, 1988; 146396 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Qimiao Si- Welch Foundation, 2005; 146397 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - King Walters Research Innovation Fund, 1999-2005; 146398 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Worden Chair for Physics, 1994; 146399 (Box 1, Folder 28)